School of Mathematics and Physics, The University of Queensland

■ daniel@vfryer.com | 😭 danielvfryer.com | 🖸 frycast | 💆 _frycast

I'm an early career PhD data scientist, and I'm in the rare position of having combined a rigorous understanding of applied statistics with strong skills in computer science, software engineering, and collaboration on technical projects. I have worked independently, as a researcher, project leader, and software developer, on multiple large exploratory and confirmatory analysis projects, and on research software development projects. I am great at working in messy unprocessed "big" data scenarios, involving local and cloud based SQL database management systems. I liase with statisticians, scientists, medical professionals, and executives, and I work with local and international partners, to deliver analysis and preprocessing pipelines that deliver security, confidentiality, interactivity / usability, modularity / reusability, documentation, collaboration, and machine learning / statistical rigour. I have written many private and open source R packages, two of which are currently on CRAN. I teach meta-analysis to Master's students, and I teach database design and SQL programming to professional statisticians and social scientists. I also currently serve as a council member and deputy Communications Officer at the Statistical Society of Australia, as well as technical sub-editor at the Australian & New Zealand Journal of Statistics. In my spare time I enjoy camping, video games, exercise, tasty food, and good conversation.

Education

The University of Queensland

Saint Lucia, QLD, AU

PhD | Statistics and Mathematics

2019-Current

• Explaining, exploring and clustering with non-linear and complex data

La Trobe University Melbourne, VIC, AU

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE | MATHEMATICS AND STATISTICS WITH FIRST CLASS HONOURS (WEIGHTED AVERAGE MARK: 97)

• Random fields: Long memory, and R for cosmology

Experience

The University of Queensland Melbourne, Victoria, AU

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS

2021-Current

2020-Current

2018-Current

2019-2019

Saint Lucia, QLD, AU

2014-2018

• Al for Pandemics and IDDO/ISARIC partner program

Monash University Melbourne, Victoria, AU

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

• Politics & International Relations

The University of Queensland

CASUAL INSTRUCTOR | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS 2020-Current

• Master's of Data Science project support

University of Auckland Auckland, Auckland Region, NZ

COURSE INSTRUCTOR | NEW ZEALAND SOCIAL STATISTICS NETWORK • Introduction to SQL for academics and professionals

La Trobe University Melbourne, VIC, AU

SESSIONAL LECTURER | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND STATISTICS

2018-Current

• Master's level meta-analysis | Master's level database fundamentals

The University of Queensland Saint Lucia, QLD, AU

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS

• Digital phenotyping for transdiagnostic clustering and psychiatric prognosis

La Trobe University Melbourne, VIC, AU RESEARCH SOFTWARE DEVELOPER | DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS 2018-2019

· Spherical data analysis in R on the HEALPix grid

Service

Statistical Society of Australia Melbourne, VIC, AU COUNCIL MEMBER | COMMUNICATIONS OFFICER 2020-Current **Dimension Reduction and Meta Analysis Research Group** Melbourne, VIC, AU MEMBER | WEBSITE MAINTAINER 2017-Current **Australian & New Zealand Journal of Statistics** Melbourne, Victoria, AU TECHNICAL SUB-EDITOR 2020-2020 **Campus Consultancy** Melbourne, VIC, AU SENIOR MENTOR AND FOUNDING MEMBER 2017-2019 **Research School on Statistics and Data Science** Melbourne, VIC, AU PEER REVIEWER (3 ARTICLES) 2019-2019 **Journal of Open Source Software** Melbourne, VIC, AU PEER REVIEWER (1 ARTICLE) 2019-2019 **Victorian State Emergency Services** Melbourne, VIC, AU **EMERGENCY FIRST RESPONDER** 2017-2018 La Trobe University Mathematics and Statistics Society Melbourne, VIC, AU VICE PRESIDENT | NEWSLETTER EDITOR 2016-2016 In2Science Melbourne, VIC, AU MENTOR | MATHEMATICS SCHOOL OUTREACH Awards **Future Superstars Award** Saint Lucia, QLD, AU THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND, FACULTY OF SCIENCE 2021 Vice Chancellor's Sessional Teaching Award Melbourne, VIC, AU LA TROBE UNIVERSITY, NA Three Minute Thesis | People's Choice Saint Lucia, QLD, AU THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND, SCHOOL OF MATHEMATICS AND PHYSICS Pitching Research Competition | Best Written and Oral Pitch University-Wide Saint Lucia, OLD, AU THE UNIVERSITY OF QUEENSLAND, BUSINESS SCHOOL 2019 Pro Vice Chancellor's Commendation (awarded four times) Melbourne, VIC, AU LA TROBE UNIVERSITY, UNIVERSITY-WIDE 2018 **Department Prize in Fourth Year Statistics | Best Performing Student** Melbourne, VIC, AU LA TROBE UNIVERSITY, DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND STATISTICS David Myer's Medallion | La Trobe's most prestigious undergraduate award Melbourne, VIC, AU LA TROBE UNIVERSITY, COLLEGE OF SCIENCE, HEALTH AND ENGINEERING Silver Scholarship | Community Involvement and Dedication to Mathematics Melbourne, VIC, AU LA TROBE UNIVERSITY STUDENT UNION, UNIVERSITY-WIDE **Department Prize in Third Year Statistics | Best Performing Student** Melbourne, VIC, AU LA TROBE UNIVERSITY, DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND STATISTICS Prof CJ Eliezer Prize in Second Year Mathematics | Best Performing Student Melbourne, VIC, AU LA TROBE UNIVERSITY, DEPARTMENT OF MATHEMATICS AND STATISTICS 2015 Prof Jim Morrison Prize in Chemistry | Best Performing Student (awarded twice) Melbourne, VIC, AU LA TROBE UNIVERSITY, SCHOOL OF MOLECULAR SCIENCES

Publications.

LA TROBE UNIVERSITY, UNIVERSITY-WIDE

La Trobe Award in Community Engagement | Volunteer Efforts

Pipeline

Melbourne, VIC, AU

2014

D Fryer, I Strümke, H Nguyen	arXiv
Shapley values for feature selection: the good, the bad, and the axioms	2021
HD Nguyen, D Fryer, G McLachlan	arXiv
ORDER SELECTION WITH CONFIDENCE FOR FINITE MIXTURE MODELS	2021
M Terrett, D Fryer, T Doody, H Nguyen, P Castellazzi	arXiv 2020
SARGDV: Efficient identification of groundwater-dependent vegetation using synthetic aperture radar	arXiv
A BINARY-RESPONSE REGRESSION MODEL BASED ON SUPPORT VECTOR MACHINES	2020
Published	
D Fryer, M Li, A Olenko	Astrophysics Source Code Library,
b Fi yei, M Li, A Oteliko	ascl:
RCOSMO: COSMIC MICROWAVE BACKGROUND DATA ANALYSIS	2020
D Fryer, M Li, A Olenko	The R Journal
RCOSMO: R PACKAGE FOR ANALYSIS OF SPHERICAL, HEALPIX AND COSMOLOGICAL DATA	2020
D Fryer, I Strümke, H Nguyen	Frontiers in Applied Mathematics
Shapley Value Confidence Intervals for Attributing Variance Explained	and Statistics
D Fryer, H Nguyen, P Castellazzi	2020
K-MEANS ON POSITIVE DEFINITE MATRICES, AND AN APPLICATION TO CLUSTERING IN RADAR IMAGE SEQUENCES	2020
	Research School on Statistics and
D Fryer, A Olenko	Data Science
SPHERICAL DATA HANDLING AND ANALYSIS WITH R PACKAGE RCOSMO	2019
D Fryer, H Nguyen, P Orban	Journal of Open Source Software
STUDENTLIFE: TIDY HANDLING AND NAVIGATION OF A VALUABLE MOBILE-HEALTH DATASET	2019
DV Fryer, I Strumke, H Nguyen	PeerJ Computer Science
MODEL INDEPENDENT FEATURE ATTRIBUTIONS: SHAPLEY VALUES THAT UNCOVER NON-LINEAR DEPENDENCIES	2021
Presentations and events	
IEEE Symposium Series on Computational Intelligence	Brisbane
K-MEANS ON POSITIVE DEFINITE MATRICES, AND AN APPLICATION TO CLUSTERING IN RADAR IMAGE SEQUENCES	2020
Talk and conference publication	
Statistical Society of Australia	Melbourne
EARLY CAREER INDUSTRY SHOWCASE, CHIEF EVENT ORGANISER	2020
6 panelists, 180 attendees https://vimeo.com/ssavic/20200922-showcase	
Victorian Research Students Meeting in Probability and Statistics EXPLAINING, EXPLORING AND CLUSTERING WITH NON-LINEAR AND COMPLEX DATA	Melbourne 2020
Building the Melbourne research student community	2020
UQ Research Video Pitch	St Lucia
FORECASTING PSYCHIATRIC SYMPTOMS WITH DIGITAL PHENOTYPING	2020
First prize. youtu.be/h-m8QwLq29Y	
UQ Three Minute Thesis Presentation	St Lucia
MACHINE LEARNING: THE BIG BLACK BOX	2020
People's choice award. vimeo.com/434959101	
RSSDS2019 Poster Presentation	Melbourne
SPHERICAL DATA HANDLING AND ANALYSIS WITH R PACKAGE RCOSMO • Poster and Springer book chapter	2019
Poster and Springer book chapter UseR!2018 Conference	D.J.L
Cosmic Microwave Background data analysis with R	Brisbane 2018
Description of the second Data analysis with R	2010

• R package published on CRAN. https://youtu.be/7KBsguOlEHs

Australian Mathematical Sciences Institute Summer Research School

Melbourne

FUNCTIONALS OF LONG-RANGE DEPENDENT FIELDS AND HERMITE DISTRIBUTIONS

2017

• Summer Research Scholarship recipient. vrs.amsi.org.au/daniel-vidali-fryer-2017/

UNSW Statistical Challenges in Astronomy

• Fostering new collaborations in statistics and astronomy

Sydney

LIGHTING TALK: A NEW R PACKAGE FOR COSMOLOGY

2017